So we back again now and we start to implement the exciting part which is using
the comment prompt or the CLI. For now, as you recall in our last video, when we
want to use IP addresses or we configure the static IP address, if I want to
seize IP address that I have configured, which was 120, I need to type either the
legacy comment, which is if config. Okay, this is the legacy comment, or there is the
new more comment, which is actually I prefer it because it is very simple. You
can type IP space A. If you can see here, it doesn't matter the loop back
interface, since it is a logical interface, no need to use it or configure it.
This is actually the physical interface starting with DNS, okay, and this is
our IP address with the subnet mask because it is starting from 0.2 to 5.5.5.5.5.5.0.
Actually, if I want to see the default route or the default route, I need to
issue another comment. If I want to use DNS, I need to issue another one, so IP
route here, as you can see, it is the default route, which is 100.1, it is the static
route that we made or create in the previous video, and if I want to see the
DNS, I need to type get catch file or read file, which is something like in the
windows, which says like host file, it is a file containing all of the naming
servers that I have, the primary and secondary, and if you can remember, we
configured only one DNS, one primary, we didn't configure the secondary DNS, so we
need to type catch, ETC, and resolve, and take care to write it correctly because
it is a sensitive, okay, as you can see here, we have only one name server, which
is 888 of Google. So great, let's start now with setting, try to check first host
name, by issuing this comment, host name, control, okay, let's see what the
server is named, okay, by default, there is no static host name, as you can see
here, and let's try to set the host name by using the comment line, so we need
to type the sudo, because I need the super user privilege to make the change
like that, and we'll type host name, control, and we'll type, for example, here set
host name, and make it devops server, for example, and when I press enter, need to
type my password, as expected, and no more is not in the sudo, okay, and this is
very normal, I need to add this user to be in the sudo or file, so that he can make
or use the super user privilege, there is a legacy method to add it to the super
user file, and there is a newer method to add it to the wheel group, which is
contained in the sudo or file, so let's start with, or let's make it by using
the newer method, by adding it to the wheel groups, so first I need to
switch user, need to switch of course to the rules, let's type the password
of the rules, okay, as you can see now, the comment changes from this one,
$2 this one of hashtag, because now I am an administrator, okay, perfect, so to add the user,
I need to type sudo of course, and I need to type this comment user mode, user
modification -a, g to add is to some group, and this group will be named wheel, okay, and
let's type the name of this, let's click on enter, and boom, now we are, or this
user is in the sudo word, but to try to execute any comment, I need to log on,
log off and log on, so let's do it quickly, I will log off and log on, and try to
execute the comment again.
Okay, here I am back again, I will open the terminal, and let's type the comment again,
okay, I can search, I can type it again from the history by using the apparel, so do host
name, and let's set it to the ops server, okay, now we should be okay, so if I want to
validate it, I can type host name, control, and static host name is successfully changed
as you can see now, perfect, so now we have changed the host name after adding the user
and the model successfully to the sudo word file, so let's move with another task or another
tutorial, so now we need to make, or make sure that this server is protected by using
the firewall, so the first thing to do here is to make sure that the firewall, it should
be by default installed, but anyway, we will install it, and if it is already installed
it will inform us, okay, so to install it, we need to type the sudo, system, control, and
we'll type firewall, daemon, to install the firewall, daemon, sorry, just the comment, it
is a missed typo, so I need to type it correctly, the error here that I need to use dnf package
manager, to install it, set my bed, okay, so to the nf, this is the default package manager
okay, so now, as you can see here, this package, okay, is already installed, if it's not
installed, it will take some time, maybe 5 to 10 minutes until it is installed, and there
is no dependencies, issues, and everything is okay, perfect, so now let's clear the screen,
let's now try to make sure that the firewall daemon is run, it's okay, so let's type
sudo, system, control, and let's enable first firewall d, okay, sudo, system, system,
start, not enable, let's start it and then enable it later, okay, system, ctl, ctl, not
lt, this is a case sensitive, okay, so system, control, start firewall daemon, and let's
enable it after that, okay, so you should now be cool, and the firewall daemon should
run successfully, if I want to make sure that it is okay, so I need to type the same
command of system, control, and status, and now it's okay, we can see that it is active and
run, okay, that's perfect, and if we show the process IDs runs in, so I'm everything, okay,
that's perfect, so now let's try after make sure that the firewall is installed and configured,
let's do some basic configuration, what basic configuration we can do, actually we can,
after we check that the firewall is okay, we have different type of zones, let's check
what is available zones in firewall, for example I may be at work, I need public network,
if I have outside in airports or any public place, for work, if I am in the work, I need
to access some interfaces, maybe use the special access, where my mom's work network,
and also if I am at home, I need another zone, okay, so to list the zones, I need to
type this command, okay, it would say that these, these are all the zones that I have from
internal trusted block, it is, okay, so these are all the zones that I have, all types
of, so by default it is already made that we have a default zone of trusted, okay, or the
public, sorry, so I can set any interface to be created, to be set automatic to the public
or untrusted zone, okay, this is the interface, which you can see, not secure, because
it is failing the internet, it is the public one, the trusted internal, are the one with
more security, B and Z are the zones or can be the zone between the two firewalls, for
example, so let's set the default zone, okay, this already set the public to be the default
zone for any network interface that I have, okay, perfect, so now let's configure or allow
some connectivity, I want to allow some connectivity to the server to maybe access it,
supposing that I installed it using only a common prompt or server core, I don't have access
to the GUI, so I need to set special access to it like SSH to come to make some common,
execute some common, run some comments on it, I need maybe to upload some files, so I need
to enable protocols like FTP, maybe I need to install some services like Genix, Apache,
any web server on it, I need maybe to use any backend services or I install maybe SQL
on it, PHP, something like that, so I need maybe SQL access or access to support
3D to 2D SQL, okay, so we can sum up.